嘿, 你们好
hey, what's up guys
我是Cherno, 欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
my name is Cherno, welcome back to my OpenGL series
所以, 上次, 我们讨论了关于着色器的一切
so, last time, we talked all about shaders
并且我们基本上讲了什么是着色器
and we basically just went through what shaders are
以及着色器的原理
and how they work
一定要看看那集视频
definitely check out that video
如果你没看过的话, 这个链接已经在那里了
if you haven't, already this link up there
你需要知道着色器的原理
you're gonna need to know how shaders work
因为今天, 我们将要写一些着色器
because today, we're going to write some shaders
并且我真的很高兴
and I'm actually really happy
我们上个视频专门讨论了着色器
that we dedicate last video to just talking about what shaders
实际上要求我今天不必做太多讨论的内容
actually asked that I don't have to do much talking today
而我就可以去写一些代码了
and I can actually write some code
所以我们要开始了
so we're gonna just jump in
那么我们要开始写代码了
and we're gonna start writing some code
如果你还没有我们现在写的所有代码
if you don't have all of the code that we've written up to this point yet
你可以在播放列表中浏览所有的视频
you can either go through all of the videos in the playlist
并确保你的一切都是最新的
and just make sure you've got everything up to date
或者你实际上也可以访问patreon.com/TheCherno, 帮助支持这个系列
or you can actually go to patreon.com/TheCherno helps support the series
然后获得一集接一集所有的最新代码
and get access to all the code episode by episode up to this point
并且以后也是如此
and going on into the future as well
让我们开始写一些着色器代码吧
let's dive in and write some shader code
所以就快速过一遍
so just to quickly go through
到目前为止, 我们写的所有代码
all the code that we've kind of got so far
或者至少是比较重要的部分
or at least the important parts
在我们配置好OpenGL之类的东西之后
after we kind of finish like OpenGL and all that
基本上, 我们是在创建一个顶点缓冲区
we're basically creating a vertex buffer
这些顶点位置是连续的
which is consistent of these vertex positions
位置是我们当前指定的唯一属性
positions are the only attributes that we're currently specifying
然后我们指定该缓冲区的布局
we then specify the layout of that buffer
以及绑定这些属性到一个特定的索引, 索引0
as well as kind of bind these attributes to a certain index,
在本例中, 索引0访问一个顶点属性指针
index zero in this case, by a vertex attribute pointer
然后在渲染循环中
and then inside our render loop
基本上, 我们只是清除屏幕
we basically just clear the screen
画出当前绑定的缓冲区, 也就是这里的这个
draw the currently bound buffer, which is this one over here
然后我们交换缓冲区, 就是这样
and then we just swap the buffers, and that's it
我们不需要绑定任何东西
we don't bother on binding anything
或者我们真的不需要的任何东西
or anything like that we don't really need to
我们做的一切就在清除
all we're doing is we're clearing
然后画这个三角形
and we're drawing this triangle
现在让我们来写一个着色器
now let's go ahead and actually write a shader
实际上, 我们需要做的第一件事
the first thing we actually need to do
这有点无聊
this is a little bit tedious
所以我想尽快过一遍
which is why I kind of want to run through this as quickly as possible
但基本上, 我们要在这里定义一个新函数
but basically, we're going to define a new function here
它基本上是静态的
which is basically it's going to be static
因为我不希望它链接到其他翻译单元或c++文件
because I don't want it to link into other translation units or c++ files
它会返回一个整数
it's going to return an integer
并且它会被称为CreateShader
and it's going to be called CreateShader
我们实际上要传入两个字符串
and we're actually going to take in two strings
const std::string& vertexShader
const std string vertexShader
和const std::string& fragmentShader
and const std string fragmentShader
在函数里面
and inside here
我们要编写编译这两个着色器所需的代码
we're going to write the code necessary to compile these two shaders
现在，在这种情况下
now, in this case
我们要做的就是, 传入着色器实际的源码作为这些实际的字符串
all we're doing is, we're taking in the actual source code of the shaders as these actual strings
所以我们需要提供两个着色器
so we're providing two shaders
一个顶点着色器和一个片段着色器
a vertex shader and a fragment shader
这些字符串只是实际的源代码
these strings are just meant to be the actual source code
现在着色器可以来自不同地方的变体
now shaders can come from a variety of different places
我们可以照字面地直接写一个字符串
we could literally just write a string
在我们实际的c++应用中
in our actual c++ application
这包含了我们地着色器
which contains our shader
这就是我们今天要做的事情
which is what we're going to do today
为了简单起见
just for simplicity's sake
但你也可以从文件中读取它们
but you can also read them in from a file
你可以从网上下载
you can download them from the internet
你可以把它们作为二进制数据读入
you can read them in as kind of binary data
有很多不同的方式, 你可以编译着色器
there's a lot of different ways that you can actually kind of compile shaders and
进入着色器编译阶段
get to the shader compilation stage
在本例中
in this case
我们会为OpenGL提供一个字符串
we're going to provide OpenGL with a string
归根结底, 你还是需要为OpenGL提供一个字符串
at the end of the day, you still need to provide OpenGL with a string
那是你的着色器源码
which is your shader source code
通常,  你会想要从文件中获取这些
usually, like you might want to be taking that in from a file
或者类似的东西
or something like that
但现在, 我们只能
but for now, we're just going to be
我们将把它们作为字符串读入
we're just going to be reading them in as strings
我们要把它们写出来
and we're going to write them
在我们的c++应用中
in our c++ application
我想下一集
I think next episode
我们实际上要看一下
we're actually going to take a look at
在一个更专业的应用中, 我喜欢如何处理着色器
how I like to deal with shaders in a more professional application
我们会写一些代码来简化更多的着色器
and we'll kind of write some code to basically simplify the further shaders
我们将 在这个系列中写的
that we're going to write in this series
但现在, 我们只关注
but for now, we're just focusing on
如何实际创建着色器
how to actually create shaders
所以也是这个函数的主要目的
so basically the purpose of this function is to do
有几件事, 但基本上
well a couple of things, but fundamentally
我们需要向OpenGL提供我们实际的着色器源代码
we need to provide OpenGL with our actual shader source code
我们的着色器文本
our shader text
我们想让OpenGL编译那个程序
and we want OpenGL to compile that program
将这两个链接到一个独立的着色器程序
link these two together into a single shader program
然后给我们一些那个着色器返回的唯一标识符
and then give us some kind of unique identifier for that shader back
这样我们就能绑定那个着色器并使用它
so that we can actually bind that shader, and use it
和顶点缓存区一样
the same as like we did with our vertex buffer
就是我们实际上生成了缓冲区
what we actually generated buffer
并且我们获得了它返回的id
and we get an id back
当我们想要绑定它的时候
and then whenever we want to bind it
我们可以绑定那个缓冲区id
we can just bind that buffer id
所以如果我们回到这里
so if we scroll back over here
让我们开始写代码
let's start writing that code
所以我们要做的第一件事就是创建一个程序
so the first thing we need to do is create a program
现在这里, 我们生成的缓冲区方式
now here, we kind of generated buffers
基本上和这里一样的
that's basically the equivalent here
我们基本上只需要输入glCreateProgram
we basically just type in glCreateProgram
再说一次, 这是迷人的OpenGL, 它是不一致的
now again, this is lovely OpenGL being completely inconsistent
这个函数不需要传入整数引用之类的东西
this function doesn't take in the reference to an integer or anything like that
或指定的整数
or appointed to an integer
它实际上会返回一个无符号整数
it actually returns an unsigned integer
所以我们需要做的就是, 在开头这里
so what we're going to do is, at the beginning
这里写上 unsigned int program = glCreateProgram()
this write unsigned integer program equals glCreateProgram
继续, 不知道他们为什么决定他们的api如此不一致
again, no clue why they've decided to be so inconsistent with their api
但是, 嘿, 这就是OpenGL
but, hey, this is OpenGL
所以, 我们接下来需要做的就是, 创建我们的两个着色器对象, 所以
so, the next thing we need to do is, create our two shader objects, so
就是顶点着色器和片段着色器
vertex shader and fragment shader
并且这基本上又是OpenGL的模板代码
and this is basically just kind of some OpenGL boilerplate code again
unsigned int, 我们就叫这个vs吧
unsigned int, we'll call this one vs
就是等于glCreateShader()
which is going to just be equal to glCreateShader
并且这里将是
and this is going to be
着色器的类型
what the type of the shader
它在这种情况下就是GL_VERTEX_SHADER
which in this case is going to be GL_VERTEX_SHADER
现在实际上, 将会有很多重复的代码
now, a lot of code is actually going to be the same
因为总的来说, 我们只是在尝试编译两种不同类型的着色器
because basically, we're just trying to compile two different types of shaders
但给OpenGL提供我们源码的处理之类的操作, 实际上
but the process of giving OpenGL our source code and all that stuff is actually
在顶点和片段着色器之间非常非常像
very very similar between vertex and fragment shaders
所以实际上, 我将去把它抽象到它自己的函数中
so I'm actually going to just abstract this out into its own function
这样我就可以调用那个函数两次
so that I can call that function two times
而不是写一大堆重复的代码
and not have a bunch of code duplication
所以我在这儿上面
so I'm going to go up here
就写 static unsigned int CompileShader()
and I'm going to go static unsigned int CompileShader
并且第一个参数就是 const std::string& source
and it's going to be const std::string source
以及我相信GL_VERTEX_SHADER实际上就是
and I believe GL_VERTEX_SHADER is actually
它就是一个整数
it's just an integer
我不认为他们真的需要
I don't think they really need to
让我们看看glCreateShader()需要什么参数, 一个GLenum类型的
let's just see what glCreateShader takes in, GLenum
并且我认为如果搜索这个GLenum, 在这儿, 只用了vs的辅助工具
and I think if I search for GLenum, here, just using visual assist
它是一个无符号整型
it's an unsigned int
所以, 我这里(CompileShader第二个参数)就是unsigned int type
so, I'm just going to write unsigned int type
现在因为一些原因, 我真的不喜欢用OpenGL的内置类型
now I don't really like using OpenGL's built-in kind of types for several reasons
但主要只是因为
but mainly just because
我倾向于使用多种图形接口
I tend to use multiple graphics apis
那么如果我开始为一切(数据)使用OpenGL的类型
and if I start using OpenGL's types for everything
我可能需要到处包含OpenGL, 诸如此类的操作
that I kind of need to include OpenGL everywhere, and all that stuff
所以如果你看到我在这种情况下使用无符号整型, 而不是GL
so if you're seeing me kind of use unsigned int in these cases instead of GL
而不是使用GLuint
instead of kind of what is it a GLuint
我想是这样写的
it was just written like this, I think
对, 我不喜欢使用这样的类型
yeah, I don't like using types like this
我更喜欢使用c++类型, 不论在哪儿
I much preferred just using they're all c++ types which they are anyway
那只是因为我更倾向于处理多种图形接口
that's just because I tend to deal with multiple apis
并且这就是我习惯的
and that's what I'm used to
记住这一点, 你以前可能见过
just keep that in mind, you might have seen that before
这绝对是我建议你做的
it's definitely what I would recommend doing
好吧, 如果我们回到这里
okay, so if we scroll back up here
就是CompileShader()
CompileShader
让我们移动我们之前在这写的这个代码吧
let's just move this code that we've got over here
实际上, 我可能把这个glCreateShader()移到这里
actually I might just move this glCreateShader over here
然后再做
and then just make
让我们看看, unsigned int id = glCreateShader()
let's see, unsigned int id equals glCreateShader
好了, 同样, 我们可以CompileShader()赋值给这个(vs)
okay, common, we can kind of assign this to be CompileShader
这就是顶点着色器
this will be the vertex shader
以及我将指定它就是我们的GL_VERTEX_SHADER
and I'll specify that it is our GL_VERTEX_SHADER
实际上, 我想我会重新排列这些参数
I actually think I'm going to reorder these arguments
因为实际上, 指定第一个参数为类型(type)可能更有意义一点
because probably makes more sense to actually specify the type first
然后这个实际的源码
and then the actual source code
所以让我们很快重新排列这些
so let's just reorder these real quick
没什么大问题
no big deal
好了, 好了, 酷
there we go, all right, cool
让我们继续写我们的CompileShader函数
so let's continue one with our CompileShader function
我可以做的一个事情就是
one thing that I can do is
事实上, 我想要的是
actually gonna to want to expect is
而不是我们实际上提供C++数据字符串
instead of us actually providing a c++ data string
实际上它需要一个原始字符串
it's actually going to want a raw string
所以我就这么写, const char* src, 表示source;
so I'm just going to write const char src for source
然后让它等于source.c_str()
and then just set this equal to source dot c string
我们可以这样写
which we can write like this
这只返回一个指针, 正如你所见
this just returns a point, as you can see
它实际上在注释中说了
it actually says in a comment
返回一个以null结尾的不可变数组的指针
return pointer to null-terminated immutable array
所以不可变肯定意味着你不应该改变这个
so immutable definitely means that you shouldn't be changing this
但同时, 这只是指向我们数据开始的指针
but also, this is just a pointer to the beginning of our data
我们也可以编写这样(&source[0])的代码
we could have also written code like this
你以前可能见过这种代码
you might have seen this kind of code before
基本上, 这只是查找字符串中的第一个字符
basically this is just looking out the very first character in the string
然后返回它的内存地址, 最后返回这个
and then returning the memory address of it which, ends up returning this
因为字符串接口已经给我们提供了c_str()
because the string api does provide us with c_str
我更喜欢写这个代码
I prefer to write this code
我需要指出一件事情
one thing I want to point out
这更多是一个C++的东西
this is more of a c++ thing
但在这个例子中, 你可以做一些疯狂的事情
but just in case, you do something crazy
source在这个指针位置需要存在, 对吧
source needs to exist at this point, right
这个字符串需要存在
this string needs to exist
这不用复制数组, 或着也不用返回一个新数组给你
this doesn't copy the array, or return to you a new kind of array
这个只返回一个在标准字符串中指向数据的指针
this returns a pointer to the data inside std string
这意味着如果你有
meaning that if you have
如果这个字符串已超出范围
if string has gone out of scope
或者别的什么, 而你仍然持有这个实际的字符指针
or something and you're still holding on to this actual char point
它将指向垃圾内存
it's going to point to rubbish memory
并且这个代码将不会运行
and this code isn't going to work
所以只要确保你的source字符串仍然有效
so just make sure that your source string is actually still alive
在你编译这个代码的时候
at the time of you kind of compiling this code
有些时候, 我看见有些人可能
sometimes, I see people kind of
你知道的, 对就是字符串, 他们说字符串或其他可以这么写
you know, yes string, they'll say string or something like that
这种代码非常危险的
this kind of code is very dodgy
我可能会为这个特定的实践做一期c++视频
I might actually make a c++ episode on this specific kind of practice
因为看起来有很多人这样做
because it seems to kind of throw off a lot of people
而我也知道原因
and I can see why
如果你需要用C++，这是很容易漏掉的
it's easy to miss if you need to c++
但根本上, 如果这只返回一个临时字符串
but basically, if this just returns kind of a temporary string
并且你用它获取c字符串
and you get the c string from it
然后那个字符串可能已经被清除了
then that string might have gotten cleaned up
可能已经
might have gotten kind of well
可能已经超出范围了
might have gone out of scope
当我们达到这行代码的时候
by the time we reach this line
这意味着这个
which means that this
这个指针指向的这块内存早已被释放了
this kind of pointer is pointing to memory that's been freed already
那么你就会得到一些错误之类的
and you'll get errors and stuff like that
这就是我建议那样做的原因
which is why my recommendation is also to kind of
如果你有一个函数
if you've got a function which
它实际上返回一个字符串去
which returns a string to actually kind of
创建一个在它之外的实际值
create an actual l value out of it
然后再处理那个
and then deal with that again
可能是对c++系列的一个评论
probably probably probably a comment for the c++ series
但我只是想把它扔到这里, 为什么不呢
but just wanted to throw it in here, why not
抱歉, 回到我们的实际代码, 让我们回到正轨
sorry, back to our actual code, let's get that on track
我们已经有了source
we've got our source
我们已经有了一个指针指向实际source的字节数据
we've got a pointer to the actual source character data
我们要做的下一件事情, 实际上就是调用glShaderSource()
the next thing we're going to do is actually call glShaderSource
这是指定我们着色器的源码
which specifies the source of our shader
你可以看到, 我们需要的第一个参数就是着色器
you can see the first thing we want is the shader
基本上就是这个id
which is just basically the id
下一个需要的参数是count
the next thing we want is count
所以我们指定的源码有多少呢, 只有一个
so how many source codes are we specifying, just one
它需要的下一个参数就是, 一个实际的
the next thing it wants is an actual
现在你注意到这儿需要两个指针
now you'll notice there are kind of two pointers here
它实际上需要一个指针
it actually wants a pointer
这是一个双精度指针
this is a double pointer
它基本上就是需要一个指针指向实际的指针
it basically just wants a pointer to the actual pointer
所以我们实际上不得不
so we actually have to
实际上我们不得不给它那个source变量的内存地址
we actually have to give it the memory address of that source variable
并且然后就是这个比较重要的length
and then the length, that's important
如果你真的不想它使用这个完整的字符串
if you don't really want it to use the whole string
或者你可以在这里指定的任何东西
or anything you can specified here
但它会被转换为空指针(nullptr)
but it's gotten cast in the null pointer
再说一次, 我鼓励你们实际上去docs.gl
again I encourage you guys to actually go to docs.gl
然后看看这些函数
and check out all of these kind of functions
并且确定你实际上已经懂了
and make sure that you actually understand
你正在运行的这些代码
kind of the code that you're running
我已经提醒了很多, 关于这个
I am mentioning a lot about
这些函数的原理
how these kind of functions work
在这个系列中, 只是经验之外的
in this series, just out of experience
但请记住, 比如, 你可以将null传给length
but remember knowing for example that you can pass null into length
就像, 如果lenghth是null
like if length is null
每个字符串就会被认为都以null结尾, 诸如此类
each string is assumed to be null terminated, stuff like that
阅读docs.gl网站真的很有帮助, 那么我会做
really does help to read the docs, and I would be
并且如果我曾经真的想学习OpenGL
and if I was actually trying to learn OpenGL
可能就像, 我认为你们大多数人都需要
probably like, I assume most of you guys are
保持这个网站打开, 在你们跟着这些视频学习的时候
keep this open, as you go along with these videos
并且在当你们确定输入这段代码的时候
and as you type this code certainly
以便于你了解正在发生的事情
so that you know kind of what's going on
OpenGL在某种意义上是非常脆弱的
OpenGL tends to be very flaky in the sense
就是如果你真的弄错了一点小细节
that if you actually get a little minor detail wrong
你可能只看见一个黑窗口
you might just see a black screen in
它可能一点也无法运行
it might not work at all
很快很快, 我们就会有一期视频关于
very very soon, we're gonna have an episode about
OpenGL的错误以及如何处理它们
OpenGL errors and how to deal with them
以及我处理它们的策略
and my strategy for dealing with them
所以, 那就快到了
so that's coming up soon
我们真的没有
we don't really
我还没完成它
I haven't done it yet
因为我们只是在画一些东西, 像三角形一样微不足道
because we're just drawing something, as trivial as a triangle
并且真的
and really that
你不会认为这会出错的
that you wouldn't expect that to go wrong
你会不会, 我的意思是会的
would you, I mean will
并且对你们很多人来说, 这可能会出错
and it can can probably will for a lot of you go wrong
但很快, 当我们开始接触一些有趣的东西的时候
but very soon, when we start to get into more kind of fun stuff
我会制作一期关于OpenGL错误的视频
I am gonna make an episode about OpenGL errors
话虽如此
but that being said
还是要保持打开文档, 去阅读它
keep the documentation open, read it
对于接口, 像OpenGL一样脆弱, 当事情出错时, 这对你几乎没有帮助
with an api, as fragile as OpenGL, that gives you so little help, when things go wrong
你需要基本上掌握文档
you've want to basically master the dog master the documentation
如果你真的想擅长OpenGL
if you want to actually be good at OpenGL
好了, 回到这儿来
okay, so going back here
我们已经指定了着色器源码
we've specified the shader source code
我们需要做的下一件事情, 实际上就是调用 glCompileShader()
the next thing we need to do is basically just say glCompileShader
以及我们需要指定要编译的对象
and we need a specify whichever we want to compile
在这个例子中就是着色器的id
which in this case is just the shader id
并且这就是为了编译实际着色器我们需要写的所有代码
and that is actually all the code that we need to write to compile the actual shader
所以我们可以返回这个id
so we can return the id
并且一切正常
and everything is good
现在, 我们没有做任何的错误处理
now, we're not doing any kind of error handling
所以我们一定需要
so we definitely need to
基本上就是语法错误之类的
basically just syntax errors and stuff like this
我们需要为了这个实际的着色器做一些错误处理
we need to do some kind of error handling for this actual shader
去看看, 可能我们只是意外地
to see, maybe we just accidentally
在我们着色器源码中忘了分号之类的一些事情
you know miss semicolon or something like that in our shader source code
我们可以很快搞定, 明白了吧
we can handle all that in a minute, okay
所以回到我们的CreateShader()
so going back to our CreateShader
复制这一行代码
we're going to duplicate this line of code
叫它fs, 代表我们的片段着色器
call it fs, for our fragment shader
输入GL_FRAGMENT_SHADER
type in GL_FRAGMENT_SHADER
并且在那里传给它片段着色器的源码
and give it the fragment shader source code over here
一旦我们完成了这个
once we've done that
我们基本上就需要把这两个着色器附加到我们的程序上
we basically need to attach both of these shaders to our program
因此, 这几乎就像编译C++代码
so think of this almost like compiling c++ code
我们有两个不同的文件
we've got two different files
那么现在我们基本上需要把它们链接到一个程序中
and now we want to basically link them into kind of one program
因此我就可以同时使用它们
so that we can well use both of them
所以我们就输入glAttachShader()
so we're going to type in glAttachShader
我们将指定需要附加到的程序
we're going to specify the program that we want to attach to
然后就是实际的着色器
and then the actual shader
所以我们需要做两次, 每个着色器一次
so we're going to do this two times, one for each shader
顶点着色器和片段着色器
vertex shader and fragment shader
然后我们将调用glLinkProgram()链接我们的程序
then we're going to link our program by calling glLinkProgram which
我们只传入程序的名字
if we just take into the name of the program
不是名称, 而是id
or rather not the name but the id
并且最后, 我们将输入glValidateProgram()
and finally we're going to type in glValidateProgram
并且这些函数也是
and these functions again are
你应该在文档中了解的一些东西
something that you should read about in the documentation
如果你真的想要明白它们是做什么的
if you actually want to understand what they do
你可以看到, 这个基本上是做什么的, 好吧
you can kind of see the basically what this does is,  well
对实际程序的验证
performs validation on the actual program
以及一些验证的状态
and the kind of status of the validation
同样也会作为一部分被保存在程序对象状态中
again will be stored as part of the program's object state
你实际上也可以调用glGetProgram()
which you can actually call kind of glGetProgram
然后查询这个实际的结果
and query what the actual result is
和所有的东西
and all that stuff
再说一次, 我鼓励你们去阅读这个文档
again I encourage you guys to read the documentation
我现在不打算解释太多
I'm not going to explain these too much right now
因为有些代码你只写过一次就忘了
because there's kind of code you write once and forget about
所以我真的认为谈论它们太多并不重要
so I don't really think it's important to talk about them too much
但一定要看看这个文档
but definitely can see the documentation
特使你的着色器有问题的时候
especially if you have problems with your shader
或者你只是想了解更多, 成为最终的OpenGL大师
or you just want to understand more, and be the ultimate OpenGL master
最后我们实际上现在可以删了我们的着色器
finally we can actually delete our shaders now
这是因为它们已经被链接到一个程序中
that's because they've been linked into a program
所以我们可以删除这些中间文件, 如果你在使用c++
so we can kind of delete the intermediates, if you will in c++
当我们编译一些东西时
when we compile something
我们得到了一些中间obj文件
we get intermediate obj files
当我们在使用微软编译器时, 它就是对象文件
object files when we're dealing with microsoft's compiler
并且最后, 我们可以删除那些中间文件
and at the end, we can kind of delete that
因为我们实际上已经得到了一个实际的程序
because we've actually got an actual program
现在它们已经存储在程序中了
now they're stored inside the program
所以我们实际上将对vs和fs调用glDeleteShader()
so we're actually going to call glDeleteShader with vs and fs
这儿也有一些像glDetachShader之类的函数
there are some other functions like glDetachShader and stuff like that
这些实际上可以删除源码
which will actually delete the source code
我不喜欢调用这些函数的原因
the reason I don't like to touch those functions
有一些原因, 首先
there's a few reasons, first of all
它们真的没有必要去清理
they're not really that necessary to even clean that up
因为它占用的内存量很小
because it's it's takes a trivial amount of memory anyway
但是保留源码的着色器是非常重要的
but having the shader of source code still around is very important
当你在处理像图形深度实体的时候
when you kind of deal with things like graphics deep body
因为如果你删除了来自显卡的着色器
because if you kind of delete the shader from the GPU
来自显卡的着色器源码
the shade of source code from the GPU
你无法验证
you can't verify
并且你不能在着色器中设置断点
and you can't kind of breakpoint it step through your shader
就像你可以使用某些NVIDIA工具那样做
like you can with certain NVIDIA tools
我们将进入其中
which we will get into
如果你分离着色器并交付源代码
if you kind of detach your shaders and deliver the source codes
因此, 你会失去很多
so that, you're gonna lose a lot of that
很多调试能力, 并且说实话
a lot of that debugging ability, and to be honest
就像很多游戏引擎一样, 它们甚至都不需要调用glDetach头
like a lot of game engines don't even bother call glDetach header
因为它实现是太小了
because it's so such a minimal
就像游戏, 根本不值得那样做
like game that it's just it's not worth it
并且这就是我们要做的一切
and that's really all we have to do
我们终于可以返回我们的程序了
we can finally return our program
现在你可能已经注意到了
now you might have noticed
我们实际上返回了一个整型
that we're actually returning an int
而这个程序是一个无符号整数
whereas this program is an unsigned int
所以我要清理这个片段
so I'm just going to clean this episode
因此, 它实际上返回一个无符号整数, 并且那就是我们的着色器
so that it actually returns an unsigned int, and that is our shader
让我们快速做一下这个错误处理吧
let's quickly do this error handling
因为我有一种感觉
because I have a feeling
当我实际上在这个着色器的时候
when I actually write this shader in a minute here
它可能会出一些问题
it's just gonna be wrong
并且我会犯个错误
and I'm just gonna make a mistake
然后我会像什么都没做一样
and then I'm gonna be like create nothing works
最后我不得不写这个错误处理代码
and I'm gonna have to end up writing this error handling code
不管如何, 所以让我们现在就写它吧
anyway, so let's just write it now
比如我们刚刚看到的glValidateProgram, 就像一些状态
much like we just read about glValidateProgram setting, like some kind of state
然后我们就能检索它
and then we can retrieve it
我们还可以检索此编译的结果
we can also retrieve the result of this compilation
编译着色器实际上不会返回任何东西
compiled shader doesn't actually return anything
然而, 如果有任何东西出错了的话, 我们无法检索它去找出问题
however, we can't query it to find out if anything's wrong
那么我们可以通过调用glGetShaderiv的方式
and the way we do that is by calling glGetShaderiv
这是我们对I和V以及所有这些的第一种介绍
now this is our first kind of introduction to I and V and all this
因为glGetShare真的是个函数
because glGetShare is really the function
iv基本上是它需要的类型
iv is basically the types that it needs
所以, 首先, 我们输入id
so, first of all, we type in the id
然后采用GLenum的形式输入参数名称
then we type in the parameter name in the form of an actual GLenum
我们知道这是无符号整型
which we know as an unsign integer
基本上这里就是一个常量
basically this is just going to be a constant here
在OpenGL中定义的
that's defined by OpenGL
在这里, 我们要获得编译状态(GL_COMPILE_STATUS)
in this case, we're getting the compile status
然后是整型参数
and then the int parameter
我们知道它只是一个整型指针
which we know is just an int pointer
所以我将输入int result
so I'm going to type in an int result
然后传入那个result的内存地址
and then passing the memory address of that result
我基本上指定了一个整数
I basically specifies that we are specifying an integer
v指定了它需要一个矢量
v kind of specifies that it wants a vector
所以数组就是这个
so an array kind of one
在这种情况下, 它实际上只意味着一个指针
in this case, it really just means that once a pointer
然后我们检查result是否等于false
then we check to see if the result is equal to false
所以如果result等于result
so if result equals GL_FALSE
现在你可能注意到了这个GL_FALSE, 如果我在这儿按alt和f12
now you might notice the GL_FALSE, if I just hit alt f12 here
GL_FALSE就是找到一个0
GL_FALSE is just to find a zero
所以如果你想, 你可以
so you could if you want
还可以用带有解释标记(!)的结果指定它
also kind of specify it for results with an explanation marked
将result保存为false
save for result as false in
我经常做这种事
I usually do stuff like that
不过我不喜欢在这里做
I don't like doing it here though
因为我们是在特指使用GL_FALSE检查
because we're specifically checking with GL_FALSE
而不是使用false或之类的东西
and not just kind of false or anything like that
这可能会更有意义一点
this kind of just makes a little bit more sense
我想观众也是这样
I think to people watching as well
所以我就保持那样做了
so I'll keep it as that
所以如果result是false的话意味着着色器编译失败了
so if the result was false means that shader did not compile successfully
现在我们实际上想做的就是获得这个错误信息
what we actually want to do now is get the error message
并且我们做那个的方式
and the way we can do that
就是基本上先检索到错误信息的长度
is basically query the error message to length first
因此我这里输入int length, 然后glGetShaderiv(id)
so if I type in int length, and then glGetShaderiv id
GL_INFO_LOG_LENGTH
你可以看到为何我喜欢OpenGL的接口
you can see why I just love OpenGL's api
因为它就是太棒了
because really it's just it's just great
然后我们指定length的内存地址
and then we'll specify the memory adress of length
这样它就可以存储这些数据了
so that it can store that data then
一旦我们有了这个
once we have that
我们实际上可以在这里构造一种堆栈分配的字符
we can actually construct just a stack allocated kind of char right here
那么这个message, 它的长度就是这个length
so a message, I'll say with the parameter length
现在
now, now
我们在这儿遇到了一点小问题
we get a little bit of a problem here
我也不喜欢这样
that I don't like either
但是, 你可以看到我不能在这里创建一个堆栈分配长度
but, you can see if I can't just create a stack allocated length here
因为length实际上是一个变量, 而不是一个常量
because length is actually a variable and not a constant
并且因为一些原因
and for some reason
在某些情况下, c++不能以任意的大小来生成栈
c++ just cannot grow the stack by an arbitrary size in some cases
我们不会
we're not gonna
但我们很好
we're we're good though
我们已经超越了这种喜剧水平
we're above this kind of level of comedy
所以我们实际上要侵入这个
so we're actually going to hack this
我仍然希望在堆栈上定义它
I still want this to be defined on the stack
我可以使用一些东西
I could use something
我可以
I could just
大多人人解决这个可能是通过在堆上创建它
most people probably solve this just by making this a heap allocation
然后稍后再删除它
and then kind of deleting it later
或者将其指定为唯一指针
or maybe assigning it to a unique pointer
或者类似的
or something like that
我不是大多人
I am not most people
我不喜欢这样做
I don't like this
我仍然希望它只是在堆栈上分配的普通字符
I still want this to just be a normal char allocated on the stack
以我要做的就是把它设为等于alloca
so what I'm going to do is actually set this equal to alloca
这个大小就是length*sizeof(char)
the size being just length times the size of char
char, 当然一种像这样小写的char
char being of course a low case char like that
好的, 我们将把这个结果转换回一个字符指针
okay, and we're gonna cast this result back to a char pointer
我们就得到了一个这样的指针
and we're gonna get a pointer to that like that
alloca是一个c函数
alloca is a function that c
实际上会给你
actually gives you
它允许你在堆栈上动态分配
which lets you allocate on stack dynamically
就像我们现在做的, 明白吧
like what we've done right now, okay
根据你的意愿使用
use at your kind of discretion
很多人不喜欢用这种东西
a lot of people don't like using stuff like this
但这没理由不用它
there's no reason for not using it
真是个不错的函数
it's a nice function
我喜欢在这种情况下使用它, 这是完全必要的
I like using it in this case, it's totally necessary
那么我们继续
and let's continue
我可能会专门为此制作一期遗漏的视频
I might actually make a super lost episode about this specifically
因为它并不像它应该的那样广为人知
because it's not as well known as it probably should be
好了, 我们要做下一件事情就是输入glGetShaderInfoLog
okay, the next thing we'll do is glGetShaderInfoLog
着色器的id, 缓冲区大小的length
shader id, the buffer size being length
然后它需要一个指针形式的实际长度
then it wants an actual length in the form of a pointer
因为一些原因
for some reason
我想这可能就是输出长度
this is going to be the output length I guess maybe
再说一次, 应该阅读文档
again should read the documentation
最后需要一个指向实际缓冲区的指针
and then finally wants a pointer to that actual buffer
所以我们就这样输入message
so we'll just type in message like that
然后我们将把message打印到控制台上
then we're going to actually print the message to the console
在这种情况下, 我将使用std::cout
I'm just going to use std cout in this case
所以, cout << message
so cout message
以及 endl
and end line
在我们真的这么做之前, 我可能会打印一个
before we actually do that, I might print a kind of
failed to compile shader
现在我们不知道它在这一点上编译失败的是哪种着色器
now we don't know which kind of shader it failed to compile at this point
所以我们实际能做的就是, 如果我们
so what we actually could do, if we were
如果我们真的冷静
if we were really cool
基本上就是检查着色器的类型
is basically just check to see what type the shader was
在这个例子中, 我们知道
in this case, we know
我们只编译顶点或片段着色器
we're only compiling either a vertex or fragment shader
所以我能做的就是
so what I could do is
如果我像这样把代码分开
if I just kind of separate this code out like this
我要做的就是
what I could do is right
type=GL_VERTEX_SHADER
type equals GL_VERTEX_SHADER
如果那是真的
if that's true
我要把它移到这里
I'm going to actually move it down here
所以你就可以看到我在写什么了
so you can see what I'm typing
如果那是真的, 我们就写vertex
if that's true, we're going to write vertex
如果它是假的, 我们就写fragments
if it's false, we're going to write fragments again
这还是有点小愉快的
this is a little bit happy
因为我们可有不止这两种着色器类型
because we could have more than just these two shader types
但我认为这可能完全没问题
but I think that's probably totally fine
我要把这行带回到这一行上
I'm going to kind of bring this line back to being on one line
但实际上我已经打开了包裹
but I've actually got wrapping turned on
所以你还是可以看到一些
so you can see a bit of it anyway
好吧, 酷
all right, cool
所以我们可以打印一条信息
so we're printing a message saying
我们编译失败的着色器类型
that we failed to compile our type of shader
然后我们再打印这个message
and then we're printing the message
最后, 我们应该通过写glDeleteShader()来处理这个结果
finally, we should kind of handle this result by writing glDeleteShader
当然, 我们的着色器编译没有成功
because of course, our shader compilation didn't work out
并且然后我们可以像0这样的一些东西
and then we can return something like zero
因为我们取的是无符号整数
because we are taken unsigned int
所以我们不能返回-1
so we can't really return -1
好了, 酷, 继续
okay, cool, there we go
现在我们不检查它是否正常或类似的东西
now we're not checking here to see if it works or anything like that
可能是断言之类的
which probably is assert or something like that
如果这不起作用
if this doesn't work out
因为它对程序的成功运行至关重要
because it's kind of vital to a program running successfully
但不管如何
but anyway
我们至少会将错误消息打印到控制台
we'll at least get the error message printing to the console
这应该足以在我们这里调试它
that should be enough to debug it in our situation here
好了, 酷, 这就是我们需要的一切
all right, cool, so that's all we need
现在我们快速写个着色器
now we can actually write a shader quickly
希望能用上它
and hopefully use it
所以现在让我们说说, 写一些着色器
so let's talk about writing some shaders now
我们要下来这里
we're going to come down here
就在我们创建这个缓冲区之后
to just after we create all this buff
我们在哪里做这个并不重要
it doesn't really matter where we do this
在使用顶点属性指针之后, 会做很多事情
much does after the kind of vertics attribute pointer on
所以首先, 我知道我们只需要输入
so first of all, we know that we can just type in
unsigned int shader = CreateShader()
unsigned int shader equals create shader
然后我们需要指定两个字符串
and then we just need to specify two strings
就是源码, 就这样
which are the source code, and that's it
那么让我们来写我们的第一个着色器
so let's kind of just write our first shader
std::string vertexShader =
std string vertex shader equals
那么现在我们就要写我们的源码了
and now we're going to write our source code
写这个可能比较烦人, 作为C++字符串
now this is a little bit annoying to write, as a c++ string
因为我们必须在每行后面加一个新行字符( )
because we have to put like a new line character after every line
一切都很烦
and all that super annoying
但不管如何, 我们都要做
but we'll kind of do it anyway
所以先让这个换行
so I'll kind of bring this down here
这样写起来可能更容易一点
to make it a little bit easier
我们首先要写的是#version 330 core
first thing we're going to write is version 330 core
这基本上只是意味着我们将使用GLSL
which basically just means that we're going to be using GLSL
这是OpenGL着色器
which is OpenGL shader
就是GL着色器语言
which is the GL shading language
OpenGL着色器语言
OpenGL shading language
version 330和core意味着它不让我们使用
version 330 and core means that it's not going to let us use
任何弃用函数, 或者类似的东西
any kind of deprecated functions, or anything like that
这将导致着色器编译
that will result in a shader compilation
因为我们只想确认
because we just want to make sure that
我们正在用最新的和最好的
we're using the latest and the greatest that we have
现在我这里不写450或440的原因是
now the reason I'm not writing like 450 or 440 here is because
我们还不需要所有这些新功能
we're don't really need all those new features just yet
当我们这样做的时候, 我们将转而使用那些更多模式的语言
when we do, we will switch to using those more mod languages
并且在这个例子中, 我们只是确保了一点额外的兼容性
and in this case, we're just ensuring a bit of extra compatibility
我需要写个换行符
I want to write a new line character
然后回车
and then I'm going to just press enter
在C++中, 你不需要像加法或类似的东西那样写
in c++, you don't need to write like plus or anything like that
如果你像这样写一些字符串
if you just write strings kind of like this
一个在另一个后面
one after the other
它们将被连接成一个字符串
they will be concatenated into a single string
好了继续, 我们有一空行
okay next, we'll have just a kind of a blank line
只是因为
just because
我确保在这儿写的是新行
again I'll make sure I kind of write new line here
我们真的不需要写新行
we don't really need to write new line
这比实际c++更适合我
this is more for me than actual c++
但不论如何, 我们实际上还是要写
but we'll actually do it anyway
然后最后的void main
and then finally void main
这就是我们着色器的主函数
this is our main function for our shader
像你看见的其他函数一样展开
just going to open it up like it was any other function you can see
搞笑的是, 我几乎已经忘了写换行符了
I'm already kind of forgetting to write new lines everywhere which is fun
定义此类着色器的另一个原因
another reason why defining these kind of shaders
而且文件要好得多
and files is a lot better
并且在下一期我们可能就会那样做
and we will probably do that next episode
这个主函数的运行方式就和
this main function works much the same way
在c++中我们实际的主函数一样
as our actual main function does in c++
当我们这里有int main时
when we actually have int main here
我们基本上只是指定这是做什么函数
we're basically just specifying what function did this
这个主函数会被调用
this main function will get called
当这个顶点着色器被调用的时候
when this vertex shader gets called
并且我们基本上在这儿想做的
and what we basically want to do in here
就是设置gl_Position
is just set gl_Position
等于我们顶点位置的属性
equal to our attribute which is our vertex position
这是我们在这里指定的
which we kind of specify over here
我们把顶点属性指针放在索引0处
and we take in our vertex attribute pointer at index zero
所以我们如何访问这个数据
so how do we access this data
如何在实际着色器中访问这两个浮点数
how do we access these two floats in our actual shader
我们需要在这里指定实际属性
well, we need to specify the actual attribute up here
所以我要在这里增加一些空间
so I'm going to kind of add some space here
然后指定属性, 我将这样做
and then specify the attribute, and I'm going to do this
基本就是输入in vec4 position
by basically typing in in vec4 position
然后在这行的开头
and then at the beginning of the line
我将指定
I'm just going to specify that
这个实际属性位于索引0处
this actual attribute is located at index zero
我这样做只是通过写
and the way I'm doing that is just by writing
像这样的layout(location = 0)
a layout location equals zero like that
然后才是in vec4 position
and then in vec4 position
所以这个0应该和这个0匹配
so this this zero is should be matching up with this zero
因为它就是我们属性的索引
because it is the index of our attribute
所以有一件事你可能已经注意到了
so one thing you might have noticed
就是我使用了vec4
is that I'm taking an vec4
然后, 我实际上给它了一个vec2
however, I'm actually giving it a vec2
为什么我要那样做
why am I doing that
首先, 无论如何, 这最终都需要是一个vec4
well, first of all, this needs to be a vec4 eventually anyway
因为gl_Position实际上是个vec4
because gl_Position is actually a vec4
并且我们不能把vec2赋值到vec4
and we can't just assign a vec2 to a vec4
我们可以把这个改成vec2
we could change this to be a vec2
但然后, 我们实际上不得不把它转成vec4
but then we actually have to kind of convert it into a vec4
通过传入position.xy
by taking in position x y
然后指定我们想要的其他值
and then kind of specifying whatever we want for the other values
可能像0和1之类的一些值
which would probably be something like zero on one
我们真的不想那样做
we don't really want to do that
取而代之的是我们实际可以
instead what we can do is actually
不管如何, 让OpenGL把它转成vec4
get OpenGL to convert this into a vec4 anyway
记住, 它知道这是一个vec2
remember, it knows this is a vec2
它知道这是一个两个分量的矢量
it knows this is a two component vector
因为我们在这儿写了2
because we've written two here
这就是它知道转换这个的原因
that's why it knows to cast this
并且因为它是一个实际位置
and because it's an actual position
它将设置第4个分量
it's going to set the fourth kind of component position
双精度实际上是一个, 应该是这样的
double w to actually be one which, which is what it should be
如果我们的矢量是一个实际的位置矢量
if our vector is an actual positional vector
我们可以在OpenGL中多谈一点数学
we might talk a little bit more about mathematics in OpenGL
以及矢量的原理等等, 在未来的视频中
and how vectors are working all that in a future video
但只需知道那个, 这就是我们现在运行的
but just know that, this is what we're running for now
好了, 酷, 看起来没什么问题
okay, cool, that looks pretty good
这就是我们在顶点着色器中实际要做的一切
that's actually all we need to do in our vertex trader
所以让我们以分号结束这个吧
so let's just end that with a semicolon
那么就让我们再写一个片段着色器吧
and let's write a fragment shader
我将复制这里的所有代码
I'm going to copy all this code here
粘贴在下面
come down here
就叫它fragmentShader
call this fragmentShader
我不需要任何这种layout的东西
I don't need any of this kind of layout stuff
但我需要做的就是记住
but what I do need to do remember
片段着色器应该输出一种颜色
is that fragment shader should be outputting a color
所以我可以保持这个layout(location = 0)在这儿
so I can just I can keep layout location equals zero here
如果我喜欢, 其实没必要
if I like, it's not really necessary
不管怎样, 默认值都是零
it will be zero by default anyway
但我只是想把这里改成out vec4
but I'm just at changing this to be out vec4
然后叫它color
and then I'll just call this color
这个version 300就保持在那儿
this version 330 stays the same
主函数依旧
main function stays the same
但在这里, 我们实际上指定了要输出的颜色
but here we actually specify what color we would like to output
让我们试试红色吧
let's try red
所以我就写color =  vec4()
so I'm going to write color equals vector
1.0, 0.0, 0.0
one point zero, zero point zero, zero point zero
然后是alpha值
and then the alpha value which is
我们将它设置为1, 好了, 酷
we'll set that to one, okay, cool
所以颜色和图形编程是传统的
so colors and graphics programming are traditionally
只是0和1之间的浮点数
just floats between zero and one
在一种非HDR环境中
in kind of a non HDR environment
所以基本上, 0就是黑色, 1就是白色
so basically zero is black and one is white
所以如果你习惯了颜色在0到255之间
so if you're used to colors being between zero and two fifty five
想想, 把0当作0, 255当作1
think of zero as zero and two fifty five as one
如果我这里写0.5, 那就是50%的红色
if I write 0.5, that will kind of be 50% red
这种方式就是RGBA
and the way that these go is RGB and a
现在想想RGBA和layout
now this kind of RGBA layout
所有这些都取决于实际的帧缓冲区格式
and all that kind of depends on your actual frame buffer format
但对于这种默认设置, 它肯定只是RGBA
but for this kind of default setup, it definitely is just RGBA
所以我们现在应该看到我们的三角形是红色的
so we should see our triangle as red now
这就是我们需要在这里写的所有源代码
that is all the source code that we need to write here
希望我没有犯任何错误
hopefully I haven't made any errors
不要认为我
don't think I have
只检查了确保每处都有换行符
just checking to make sure I have new lines everywhere
在那儿我没加
I don't over here
不是什么大问题, 但不管如何我还是加上
that's not a big deal, but I'll add it anyway
这对我来说很好, 酷
and that looks pretty good to me, cool
所以在CreateShader()这里
so over here on the CreateShader
让我们指定我们的顶点着色器和片段着色器
let's specify our vertex shader and our fragment shader
希望一切正常
and hopefully everything goes well
我们可以通过调用glUseProgram()绑定我们的着色器
we can bind our shader by just writing glUseProgram
然后是着色器, 就这样
and then shader, and that's it
我们实际的红色着色器现在应该用来渲染这个
our actual red shader should now be used to render this
按f5
I'm gonna hit f5
希望我们能看到一个红色的三角形
and hopefully we will see a red triangle
我们看到一个白色的三角形, 没有错误
and we see a white triangle, and no errors as well
太古怪了, 让我们来看看我做错了什么
fantastic, let's take a look at what I do wrong
好吧, 滚动到这里
okay, so just scrolling up here
让我们来看看, 噢, 好吧, 在这儿,GL_VERTEX_SHADER
and let's take a look, oh, well, there you go, GL_VERTEX_SHADER
漂亮, 我打赌你们
nice, I bet you guys
当你们看到我写的时候, 你们笑了
had a good laugh when you saw me write that
确保这显然是在编译的类型
make sure this is obviously compiling the type
所以我们不会编译两个顶点着色器
so that we're not compiling two vertex shaders
事实上, 我很惊讶它居然正常运行
I'm actually surprised that it worked well
事实上不, 我想这是一个有效的顶点着色器
actually no, I guess this is a valid vertex shader
因为我们输出的颜色只是vec4
because we are outputting color is just kind of a vec4
那很好
that's all good
这将是一个有效的顶点着色器
that would have been a valid vertex shader
这就是为什么我们没有收到任何错误
that's why we didn't get any errors
我们应该确认我们的消息是否正常工作
we should definitely have verify our messaging is working correctly
按f5
let's just hit f5
看看这是否有效
and see if this works though
好了, 太棒了
all right, fantastic
你可以看到我们有一个红色三角形
you can see that we've got a red triangle
我们的着色器似乎运行成功了
and our shaders seem to work successfully
太棒了, 让我们赶快把这个关上
awesome, let's quickly just close this
我将在我的一个着色器中故意犯一个语法错误
and I'm going to make a deliberate syntax error in one of my shaders
就在片段着色器中吧
maybe in the fragment shader
只需要把这儿这个分号忽略掉
just gonna miss the semicolon here
按f5
let's hit f5
好吧, 所以我们没有在屏幕上看到任何东西
okay, so we don't get anything on the screen
你可以在我们的日志中看到
and you can see in our log
它实际上说了, fail to compile fragment shader
it actually does say, fail to compile fragment shader
并在第9行指定我们有一个错误
and specifies it on line nine we have an error
因为单词, 它只是说语法错误, 太棒了
because words, it just says syntax error syntax error, fantastic
感谢Intel, 这是很棒的编译
thank you Intel, it's great compilement
好吧, 不管怎样, 很酷
all right, cool, anyway
让我们回到过去, 让我们恢复我们的代码
let's go kind of back, let's revert back to our code
这是一个非常非常简单的着色器
this is a very very simple shader
我们刚刚有一个红色的三角形
we've just got a red triangle running
我会再次按f5, 这样我们就可以看到了, 太棒了
I'll just hit f5 again, so we can see that, awesome
三角形, 有点酷的东西
triangle,  pretty cool stuff
还有一件事我想快速提一下
one more thing I want to quickly mention is that
你应该如何清理着色器
what you should do to clean up your shader
一旦你做完了, 也许就和那儿差不多
once you're done with it, so maybe like over here
实际上就是调用glDeleteShader
is actually called glDeleteShader
然后就是你想删除的着色器
and then the shader you want to delete
现在我们也应该为顶点缓冲区做这个
now we should also be doing this for kind of vertex buffers
并且所有这些
and all of that
事实上, 我们将把很多东西抽象成类
we are going to abstract a lot of the stuff into classes in fact
下一次, 我会向你们展示
next time, I'm going to show you
如何从文件中实际访问着色器
how to actually reach shaders in from files
以及我读取它们的策略
and my strategy for reading them in and
我是多么喜欢写着色器
how I like to kind of write shaders
因为我不喜欢
because I don't like
OpenGL让你们写着色器的方式
the way that OpenGL kind of makes you write them
等等, 所以我们会在下一期讨论这些
and all that, so we'll talk about that next episode
但当我们开始将其抽象为文件时
but as we begin to abstract this into files
我们就会讲清理之类的所有东西
we are going to cover actually cleaning up and all that stuff
因为这会变得非常重要
because that's gonna get super important
当我们有一个正在运行的程序时
when we actually have a running program
我们一直在创建和释放东西
in which we kind of create and destroy things all the time
我们不想泄露显卡内存
and we don't want to be leaking GPU memory
或者之类的事情
or anything like that
现在我们不打算在抽象方面走得太远
now we're not going to go too far with the abstraction
当然, 因为这不是游戏引擎系列
of course, because this isn't a game engine series
但我们还是要把它抽象一点
but we are still going to abstract it a little bit
这样我们就不会把整个程序写在一个文件中
so that we don't just write our entire program in one file
这将变得非常困难
it's going to get very difficult
当我们有很多代码来实际实现某些图形时
when we have a lot of code to actually achieve certain graphics
比如效果和策略等等
like effects and strategies and all that
因此应该会很有趣
so that should be a lot of fun
不管怎样, 我希望你们喜欢这个视频
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果你喜欢的话, 你可以点击这个点赞按钮
if you did, you can hit the like button
如果你想要这个视频的所有源代码
if you want all the source code for this video
因为我们确实写了很多
because we did write quite a lot
你可以访问patreon.com/TheCherno帮助支持本系列
you can go to patreon.com/TheCherno help support the series
那么你就可以访问一个私有的github存储库
and you will get access to a private github repository
那里有所有源码, 一集接一集
with all of the source code, episode by episode
所以你可以继续看你现在正在看的那一集的代码
so you can just follow along to the episode you're currently on
并且所有这些都是通过查看提交历史来实现的
and all of that by just looking at the commit history
太棒了
it's great
同样, 你也会帮助支持这个系列, 这是非常重要的
and again, you'll also be helping support the series which is very important
除此之外, 还提供了其他一些很酷的奖励
there are also some other pretty cool rewards
比如, 置顶赞助人
for example, the top tier patrons
实际上我们每个月都有一个小时的聚会
actually we have like a one-hour hangout once a month
但我们几乎什么都谈
but we just talk about pretty much anything
这是很酷的事情
it's pretty cool stuff
无论如何, 一定要看看patreon.com/TheCherno
anyway, definitely check out patreon.com/TheCherno
真的对支持这个系列很有帮助
really does help support the series
非常感谢大家
so thank you so much to everyone
帮助我们实现这一切
who's helping make this happen
和往常一样, 你可以在下方留言讨论这一集
as always, you can talk about this episode by just leaving a comment below
或者去thecherno.com/discord, 并且加入这个社区
or just going to thecherno.com/discord, and joining that community
这是很棒的
it's awesome
下一次, 我们将会做更多着色器的东西
next time, we're going do some more shader stuff
到时见, 拜
I'll see you then, goodbye